Guide to the Cameroon Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Cameroon collection
1912-2008
MS 1507
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.25
(8 boxes)
The collection consists of printed material relating to current political, economic, and social conditions in Cameroon. Also included are photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection (MS 605); Pamphlet Collection (MS 1351); African Postcard Collection (MS 1575). Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically, with photographs last. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of printed material relating to current political, economic, and social conditions in Cameroon. Also included are photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Cameroon -- Description and travel; Cameroon -- Economic conditions; Cameroon -- Politics and government; Cameroon -- Social conditions
- Original Accession, 1948-1992
  - Political organizations: press releases; bulletins; journals; newsletters, 1948-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General information pamphlets; brochures; booklets, 1952-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Government journals; papers; documents; speeches; releases, 1960-1987 (Box 1, Folder 3 - 4)
  - Popular magazines; journals; newsletters, 1969-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5 - 6)
  - Union des Populations du Cameroon (UPC): journals; documents; printed material, 1977-1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Cameroon Analyses": bimonthly newsletters, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mission de Délimitation 1912, 1913, 1914: Afrique Équatoriale Française Cameroun: picture book, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Additional Material, 1952-1998; Accession 1995-M-169
  - Additional printed materials, 1952, 1971, 1986-1998, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1931; Accession 2001-M-043
  - "Kamerun: A Case Study in German Imperialism, 1884-1905," by Harry R. Rudin, [winner of the John Addison Porter Prize, Yale University], 1931 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 194?; Accession 2003-M-066
  - Photographs [fifty-four; mainly French government information photographs of art, architecture, scenes of daily life], [194-] (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
- Additional Material, 1973-1997; Accession 2005-M-112
  Scope and Contents
  The accession contains a variety of printed matter organized alphabetically by author, title, or organization.
  - "Bebela," L'Union National des Étudiants Socialistes du Kamerun (UNESK), 1979 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cahiers d'Education Civique, no. 4, Opposition en Démocratie, Cercle Culturel Camerounais, 1993 December (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cameroon Panorama, vol. 9, no. 153 [publication of the Catholic Dioceses in Cameroon], 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cameroon 3 e Republic, no. 2, 1973 October (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Centre de Documentation, "Catalogue des Memoires 1977" [annotated bibliography] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Courage," Union Chrétiennes de Jeunes Gens du Cameroun (UCJG), no. 2, 1979 October-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Le Flambeau Revolutionaire," Patriotes Kamerunais, no. 3, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - La Gazette / The Gazette, vol. 1, no. 1 [newspaper], 1983 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Illustrated Manuel on Human Rights, no. 2, elections, Human Rights Defence Group, 1997 February (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - International Women's Club of Douala Newsletter, vol.1, no. 2, 1980 November (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Message to Southern Cameroonians at the Eleventh Hour," Cameroon Anglophone Movement (CAM), 1994 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Nouvelles du Cameroun / Cameroon News" [press release of the Cameroon embassy in the U.S.], 1978 January 26 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Punch, vol. 1, no. 1 [newspaper], 1979 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Social Democratic Front (SDF), press briefing excerpts, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "La Voix du Kamerun," Union des Populations du Cameroun (UPC), no. 32, 1982 November (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Wirba, Fr. Dinayen, "Sunday Report," vol. 3, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Additional Material, 1968-2006; Accession 2010-M-096; (1 box)
  - Le Germoir (Journal des estudiantes du Centre Universitaire de Dschang), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Afo A Kom (Revue Camerounaise d'information artistique et culturelle), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mutations Quotidien (Report on Bakassi Crisis), 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cameroon Tribune (Report on Bakassi), 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cameroun, dix ans de gouvernement Ahidjo, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - La philosophie est-elle inutile, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional material, 1950-2008; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1950-2008 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)